all right welcome back cohort 7 we're in
our second onboarding SL chapter one
slash Etc and Andrew go for it however
you want to
begin yeah uh
great so I know that
today we're covering not just chapter
one but just a more General like
introduction to
to the group and active inference um
sort of meeting uh I will kind of quick
quickly give like a rundown of this
first chapter it's not very long there's
not too much to say but um that said I
thought it'd be useful just to kind of
kind of wrangle together all these
different themes here um that we're
going to be seeing in chapter one but
also going forward for the rest of the
textbook so in chapter one we're very
quickly introduced to this general idea
that a we have uh agents which could be
seen as living biological organisms or
other kinds of self-organizing systems
um but they conceptualized as agents and
so agents take in sensory observations
and elicit actions to either realize
their desired outcomes or goals and
Andor to make sense of their world by
gaining information about it this leads
to the development of adaptive behaviors
or strategies that agents use for
navigating their environment uh this
process plays out in a recursive action
perception cycle where observations and
form agents decision making regarding
the next action they should take uh we
also learn that this this whole process
occurs at various levels of complexity
and differing time scales ranging from
the simple and rigid moment moment by
moment strategy I of nutrient seeking
bacteria up to the more complex and
flexible strategies of humans engaging
in planning to realize their goals in
the future active inference occurs at
different physical scales as well as
well from microbiology to Broad cultural
and development developmental learning
in collectives or human
societies uh one way to frame active
inferences approach uh for example is
through the neats versus scruffies
discussion in this chapter uh while
so-called scruffies lay emphasis on the
idio sequencies and specificity of
various phenomena of interests for
example different biological adaptations
neuronal Dynamics or cognitive
mechanisms uh each deserving of their
own separate bottomup research from
empirical data the so-called Meats
aspire to a set of first principles for
explaining and relating these diverse
phenomena in a more top- down fashion
while still engaging in empirical
analysis for validation and so active
inference also identifies with needs as
it lays the normative framework for
understanding the brain and mind and
their biological and cognitive
implications alongside model design and
testing for empirical analysis um we're
given a kind of General schematic of the
rest of the book uh it's separated into
two parts s the first half will focus on
Theory the second half on practice so
I'm just going to speak about the rest
of the first half um the first half
basically presents active inference as a
normal normative framework with its
distinct Concepts and theories um we're
shown a kind of conceptual road map at
how to arrive at active inference uh in
you know your respective Learning
Journey or however you would like to
view that um and there are kind of two
roads to reach active inference there's
a low road starting with bases theorem
uh which basically supplies the
mechanics of active inference uh in its
relation to what would be called the
basian brain
hypothesis uh it's basically a way of
viewing uh processes or computations in
the brain is playing out Thea basian
principles where there's prior
information uh new observations come in
there's some kind of likelihood that
relates uh prior information with new
information and then uh produces a kind
of
posterior uh result you know a
prediction about what's going on in
terms of uh inference right inferring
what is going on based on what you
thought before as well as what new
information you've received and then on
the other hand the high road in chapter
three uh coming much later begins with
the fre fre energy principle or the
necessity for agents to minimize free
energy as a proxy or upper bound on
surprisal uh in order for these agents
to survive and adapt to their
environment uh for the rest chapter 4
we'll just go a bit more into detail
about basis theorem and we'll actually
be presented with uh major kind of
Exemplar active inference models uh
those that are used for discrete time
scenarios as well as continuous time
scenarios chapter five uh the final
chapter of this uh theory part of the
book we'll then uh discuss the neural
process theory of active inference uh
which you know again begins with the
free energy principle but then also rate
how the specific quantities we find in
active inference like predictions
prediction errors Precision signals and
so on which we'll we'll discuss much
later how all these map to cognitive
functions and their constituent
physiological substrate and ronal
computations so uh through the course of
the first part of this book these first
five chapters we just repeatedly
returned to various themes uh perception
as changing one's mind action is
changing the world learning as actually
being very similar to perception but
operating at a slower time scale with
longer term impact on the inference
process going forward thus learning uh
planning is a means of selecting actions
and sequences to realize not just
current but future goals by uh kind of
kind of uh predicting forward into the
future to decide what you should do
later not just in the here and now uh
some other things like uh how to define
exploratory versus exploitative
behaviors it's a common distinction made
in various uh Sciences
Behavior Uh and and
I especially wanted to note those
because an active inference claims to
kind of uh include both kinds of
behavior within the same optimization
function for energy
minimization um as opposed to treating
them as uh separate and needing to be
manually defined uh as we'll find in
many other kind of computational
approaches like in reinforcement Le uh
agents for
example um
and that is about everything that I kind
of put together here for describing the
first part of the book um you know feel
free to obviously read the rest of the
chapter it'll talk about all the uh
other chapters in the book as well but
just focusing on part one for today so
um I guess I'd like to open up the
conversation I know that there's some
introductions at the very beginning of
the meeting so I'm not sure if we want
to go back into those but uh usually how
we do it in the textbook is just anyone
who has uh something of interest uh
about this chapter or a question they
have um they would just like to throw it
out there we could uh take things from
there there there's things that um I
have to say but I'm look in my not I I I
make notes on my trell board so if
anybody else has anything to say before
I I get to the notes I've taken on this
chat on
um I guess they could feel free I'm just
looking for my
notes sure uh Jorge you have
something yes basic question uh what is
free energy
itself like not the pr principle but
free
energ yeah so it's uh For Better or
Worse is somewhat uh complex concept but
um it's it's basically it's you can
relate it
to information Theory it's kind of like
an information theoretic quantity if
that makes any kind of sense that Mak
sense yeah so it could it could be
measured in NS for example um
and kind of the the importance of it
here is that it acts as a kind of
proxy more specifically a kind of upper
bound on another quantity that organisms
are theorized to be trying to minimize
called
surprisal and the reason why we're not
um try saying it's surprisal
minimization as opposed to free energy
minimization so surprisal as far as kind
of the basing computation that's being
played out here surprise is typically
like
intractable um it's just a a lot of um
kind of factors that need to be
marginalized along the way when when
Computing surprisal there can be kind of
this issue with integrals and so on and
so free energy in kind of mechanical
terms is just yeah an upper bound on
surprisal that is tractable so we can
compute it then on the other hand um it
still relates to something like
something like a kind of biological
realism that is you know uh organisms
have
limited uh resources in the Moment by
moment inference processes that they
undertake right so they're biological
and
metabolical um kind of constraints on on
what they're able to
do hopefully that was
helpful
yeah let me add one more by by analogy
here so from chemistry one free energy
type that people might be familiar is
the Gibbs free energy so this is the
thermodynamic free energy and so it's
like ball rolls downhill is the um
Newtonian
mechanical path of least action given
gravity candles burn given the
activation barrier is the thermodynamic
equivalent so put putting aside this the
activation energy question going
downhill means energy is dissipated as
heat but then there's some floor where
there's no more liberable energy from
that floor so free is not in terms like
free like beer free like software free a
synonym for it is like liberable or like
releasable as heat so then 1900s are
happening information and thermodynamics
are coming closer in info thermodynamics
with in a lot of different like kind of
really mechanistic ways like Land hours
limit how much heat is related to like
erasing one bit but also like
realizations that at even deeper levels
that there's these um way to think about
information in terms of also a path of
least action in an arbitrary State space
that's called basy mechanics so the ball
rolling downhill in this case is like
explaining the data better or better is
given a specific like form of families
of
equations such that there's kind of a
signal to noise and the signal is kind
of like the the floor and the noise is
more like a heat or an
entropy so it's used as an approximator
that bounds surprise minimizing surprise
is maximizing model evidence however
maximizing evidence you don't know how
high that mountain is going to go but
minimizing surprise is often more
tractable but then it itself is
intractable for another reason which
necessitates in the approximate basian
setting the usage of variational methods
because that gives an
analytical approach that's optimizable
incrementally whereas in alternative
approach to variational approximation is
Monte Carlo or sampling based methods
those are also Limited in large State
spaces but they don't require you to
compute a free energy to balance a prial
you just sample from a distribution and
then use that as your kind of empirical
data
David uh yeah I was wondering if we
could correlate it to to um
free energy in in terms of tradeoff so
like how much how much weight is
assigned to you know the predictive
nature of tradeoff itself and how much
will you gain or lose by being right or
wrong you know depending
on the the data itself and how it's
fit the accuracy minus complexity
decomposition of variational free energy
energy energy minus entropy is kind of
like the physics e flavor accuracy minus
complexity is the statistical flavor
which is that you want to reward model
fitting but penalize more parameters so
now your kind of your risk tolerance
like whether you have a preference for
smaller and you're willing to like your
point of diminishing returns is a
smaller model or whether your point of
diminishing returns is a larger model
there's like this parto Optimum
optimality manifold where if you're off
this manifold you just could simply be
doing better but then there's like a
manifold Frontier in terms of model fit
where it's like it's like a a
hyperparameter manifold where you're
doing as well as you kind of could on
that trade-off Frontier but off that
crease you're just leaving um
explanatory power on the table with the
parameters you have
or or from coming from the other side
well that's kind of the
statistical and then this is part of the
whole theme with things the the the most
likely thing is what happens like things
are doing what's
likeliest rather than what's most
rewarding because the proposal of a
secondary reward function is not even
something that seemingly Advanced
cognitive systems necessarily do but
that's what gives Unity with the dust
particle and The Rock and cognitive
modeling but then the question is how do
you explain higher order Behavior
chological Behavior Etc in terms of
novelty Aesthetics in Surprise
minimization
terms right so I mean I guess sorry my
my approach to it you know in terms of
like I come from more of like the
quantum side of things so I don't want
to inject too much of that into it but
um if you know you have a coupling with
like a bit flip right if you have a coin
with two heads like if you're just going
off the randomness of the coin flip if
you're a blind Observer you don't know
you know heads or tails what the
trade-off is going to be I mean if it's
given the outcome is always going to be
heads how can you then minimize that
into free
energy well if you're never getting an
observation then you're never able to
calculate a free energy because the free
energy is C equation 2.5 for variational
free energy it's your beliefs and an
incoming data
points so if you don't have a data point
you could do descriptive statistics on
belief but you wouldn't calculate a free
energy
quantity right so I guess the I guess
the primary question there is if a
system is determining how you're going
to answer something because of you know
learned in
Behavior due to an
assumptive prere is it doesn't that kind
of end up being deterministic and
becoming a trade-off in the long
run I'm sorry can I um make comment
regarding like my the way I think about
free energy and how it makes sense to me
like I like to think about Fields I'm
assuming everybody on everybody here
knows what a field is and I think about
the different combinations of ways that
perception and action can unravel with
perspective prior thinking about feels
from the physics point of view and
translating that to the
cognitive and Behavioral or
psychological point of
view um and you can get really more into
the woods with this in terms of like you
know mechanisms in the brain where
neurotransmitter interactions are
happening and neurom modulor
interactions are happening but um I I
I'll get into like certain points that I
made about comments I made about the
chapter in a moment but I just figured
that what makes sense to me about free
energy and just thinking about like
potential
energy in from from a a the point of
view of like how energy can be utilized
for it's utilized and think about the
degrees of freedom that's that's there
and thinking about modeling agency and
how organism
um engage their environment but also um
a number I've had a number of com
conversations regarding free energy
being generalized beyond the scope of
thinking about agents or organisms but
also in their objects and how they take
up an environment and how you can
estimate the space over time that's
taken up by those objects and then you
can encode the marov blanket and what
have you have a field you can envelop a
field uh of like the possible
interactions that can happen even from
inert objects to um systems that are
capable of agency that can actually
properly
infer and estimate over
time um uh their environment and their
circumstances leveraging things so I uh
to me that that it makes sense from that
point of view and not to not delving too
much into the details of the physics but
acknowledging okay there's the concept
of fields and I could take that in the
combinatorial options in which me as an
agent can perceive and act on my
surroundings and develop priers but
hopefully that that that that kind of uh
is applicable to addressing this like
potential energy free energy so and what
have um mean to ramble too much but I I
I was like sitting on that thought for a
few minutes and like oh I want to say
something and
hopefully it helps make a more
sense yeah I mean it's I mean not to
heavily I'm really just kind of
simplifying and abstracting certain
parts of what you said so apologies for
that but I to kind of bring it back I
think I mean if I understand David's
question right um like isn't maybe part
of the idea is like isn't supplying some
kind of Prior that's already heavily
conditioning the the process that ensues
from there such that there's a kind of
almost determinism based on your initial
starting point because we're requiring
that you have a starting point given
this is like a basian process where have
prior information necessarily involved
and I mean
it's from my understanding it's just
kind of like a description of how the
process plays out and I like the idea of
a field whenever we just look at it as
like this is a kind of space like how
you describe like like objects or beings
in their environment their you know uh
affordances within that space or field
or environment and so on and it's like
well if we were to study that as you
know scientists researchers however like
we already have a lot of starting kind
of prior
there and we're going to start trying to
model it to predict what will happen
next so I mean
it's not to sound so abstract or
conceptual but it's like we're always
kind of working with from our standpoint
kind of you know
external uh position a bunch of Prior
information and we just kind of start
there um just a couple tangential points
that uh when setting up an active
inference
model um you know there there's of
course like fitting models to empirical
data but then there's also just during
the testing phases I mean it's very
common to just
initialize with say very
uniform uh priors you know B basically
entirely uninformative priors and it's
through the capacity for like learning
or updating model parameters that the
the agent can actually adapt to the
situation and then it's it's it's its
own parameters change such that you know
it's kind of starting with new priors in
in the next round so to speak that may
be better hopefully through Min free
energy minimization better match the
environments around it um if any of that
tracks yes and just like dynamical
systems or linear aggression you can
pull back to like univariate linear
regression or
single sinusoidal oscillator dynamical
system those are kind of like the
doorway
example but then you might run a
statistical script and it does a linear
aggression on thousands of data points
or it h it has more Dimensions than a
single dimensional form so in the
textbook much as it is for for for again
the kinds of um topics that are
addressed um in the appendices linear
algebra dynamical systems probability
information
Theory those are also like their
principles are shown in the textbook but
then when it really comes down to
anything like a system of interest it's
the shape and the specific variables you
use so these are like some of the moves
and some of the
generic cues
and then like it's all about making that
jump or path from okay listening to
music in chapter 7 to here's this music
data I
have yeah that makes sense I I guess I'm
thinking in terms of Weights as well
like if we're waiting that data um like
how can you avoid overfitting on
something that's assumptive like for
example like some of the things covered
in chapter one like do go
into I guess some of some of the things
I see as um like in terms of like not
just tradeoffs but in terms of how we
approach as you were saying like just
with sensory response right like our
priors are also based on our limitations
in terms of how we can measure how we
can even understand to measure where you
know there might be extra sensory kind
of abilities that we have from a
cognitive standpoint that we're not
aware of in terms of even just in the
way our brain interacts with itself with
neuron interaction right
so um I guess it goes back kind of to
the pheromone response as an example of
something that we can't detect but
should be able to be weighted in the
data yeah I mean just as a a brief
like like one of the key
a key Concept in in active inference
whenever it comes to modeling is the
notion of like precision as a kind of
like
inverse variance uh term and that that
can kind of be viewed
as a weight or waiting system there are
a variety of different kinds of
precisions that are applied to different
variables as far as the neural process
Theory goes they're kind of related to
synaptic gain and and neural trans
transmission um but uh yeah the general
sense is that there's a kind of waiting
process going on in addition to that
again active inference uh agents who
engage in learning like many things can
be learned including like how to adjust
those
precisions uh in order to say weigh
upweight or down weight the impact of
new incoming
information um you know there there
might be an agent who uh has a
likelihood model that that Maps
observations to its own beliefs about
what's going on is that kidden states
and so it it might it might have a lot
of really
imprecise mappings like relations such
that even though it receives new a new
observation it kind of downweights the
impact of that new observation because
it
it can't it can't find a good way of
mapping it to a to a belief State such
that it can confidently update that
belief State giving them
observation so so there are these kind
of mechanics
yeah great point with gain that can be
thought of like people with audio
editing experience probably have a very
embodied sense of this but there's a way
to tune the Precision such that even a
variable signal gets collapsed to
basically the extreme case is the dero
Delta function which is just like a line
it's a it's a special distribution that
is zero everywhere and then it's
infinite in one spot so there's a
Precision setting that'll take a range
of values of thermometer readings the
height of the children in the classroom
and do something like collapse it down
to its central tendency and then also
there's gain settings that can take even
closely related data points and flatten
the
distribution the hyper priors and some
of the parameters that that come into
play in empirical basian analysis and
then like unless otherwise specified
it's like the temperature is
one but then sometimes you do write it
out more fully and then H learn or
manipulate the hyperparameter related to
the
temperature and then about action that's
the shaky hands so it's kind
depending on where it is but but that
does basically like sharpens or
blurs okay yeah I mean that's how I was
thinking of it in terms of like gradient
descent um because those are some of the
formulas that I've been you know working
on where I also have run into a few
things that I need to check where it is
zero like you were mentioning but it
also expands infinitely at that point
and contracts infinitely at that point
so that's kind
of my prior that I'm trying to work with
in terms of like if the math is correct
what inference does that have if that
collapse point will always be zero and
one right you have a binomial
distribution at that point where it's
still a choice but if it's predetermined
right you end up and I want to get too
far into the woods on that but it's just
something I wanted to kind of highlight
from what you
mentioned I want to um bring up
so there is one statement on page 10
that I think I have some confidence
that's that that that uh the rest of the
book kind of mix up for for for the
generalization I found which uh is the
this the the the the bullet I think it's
U it's the second it's the last bullet
on the on page
10 and and it's it it's a bol that says
under active inference both perception
and learning are active processes and I
quoted the part the brain is essentially
a predicted machine which constantly
predicts incoming stimuli rather than
passively waiting for them and the
comment I made about this was that I
thought it was a it wasit it was kind of
a naive assumption to assume that
there's never a situation that the brain
is passively engaging with certain
stimuli instead of constantly predicting
and this can help differentiate between
noise and relevant stimulus to be
interpreted as information so I think
that the rest of the book gets into
better detail about this but um I made a
note of that as like kind of
um a naive assumption made on page that
I I found on page 10 that um well is the
brain predicting everything coming in
around it's predicting relevant
information but I I guess I'm assuming
that the book gets real uh it seems like
I I Peak that chapter to little but it
seems like it's it's get it does it
better at spe better job at specifying
and I think that overall chapter one
does a good job providing a nice General
overview even though there's there's
some assumptions made that I think are
clarified better but
um I
also sorry about that
yeah point I made about what I found on
regarding predictive
processing happening in the
brain yeah two two quick things on this
the first is as so so so many times
there's slipping between realism and
instrumentalism if they said first we
choose to model the brain as a
predictive machine they couldn't be
wrong because they're talking about
their position to modeling but then it
slips into what the brain is so that's
that's one piece and the second thing is
it hinges on what is meant by passively
waiting that could be hanging out on the
couch but hanging out on the couch even
if your eyes weren't
cating still you would be actively
generating the periphery the sharpness
and so on so in that sense there is this
real time like now casting a vision even
if it's not cating and moving its head
and all of that but then is that passive
or
active yeah I mean how does that speak
to a dream State as well where if you
have a hyperreal dream state you know
where there's you can affect your
surroundings in the dream state not
realizing you're in the dream state
versus awaking state in the same kind of
notion of
sensory yeah well that I mean that's an
interesting question I the way I would
take them is that it still be similar to
a waking State and that you're still
a bunch of sensory information is still
kind of being delivered to you
presumably there's something going on
that is kind of actively leading you to
make the decisions or inferences that
you're making during the the dream um
but I've never actually I've never
really followed that full thought
through on thinking about how this works
in a dreaming state but that's just my
initial guess at at an answer to that
question um I think for this particular
quote yeah same point that Daniel made
earlier the flipping back and forth
using instrumentalist language sometimes
other kinds of language other times but
I I just wanted to say I think it still
relates back to kind of that you always
have priers right there's that there's
that kind of like you have prior there
and then there's computation going on if
you didn't have criers then maybe it'd
be easier to say like like you could
passively take something in but the idea
is
that you're you're coming to a situation
figuratively with information that's
going to get computed so it's like
you're involved in the process as it
work and and to make this like really
clear and be be clear about what the
alternative hypothesis to a basian
approach would be frequentism would say
okay we're getting this wave of photons
hitting our retina and we're going to do
the maximum likelihood
reconstruction so then we'll use
interpolation gaussian blur
convolutional neural net etc etc etc all
these techniques that are these inbound
processing techniques to reconstruct a
get a snapshot of the maximum likelihood
image so that is implicitly saying all
pixels have a uniform prior like I don't
know anything and I'm just going to take
one snapshot of pixels and then
reconstruct the ml um the outcome but as
soon as you start to leverage oh well
but I think it should be like the prior
one prior
frame that's literally basian analysis
then that's the Colman filter where on
one extreme it is the special case where
you're frame by frame doing a total
reestimation The Other Extreme case is
you're just making a longterm running
average blurring over all the times so
then you have this basian hyperparameter
search question how responsive should my
Colman filter be and then you have
another model in this portfolio you know
how fast should I be learning how fast
to change that all of those basian
models can be evaluated with basian
model selection using accuracy minus
complexity basian information
criteria so it's like oh okay well I'm
getting I'm still getting bang for the
buck to three but four
always you'll fit better and better but
then you're past the point of
diminishing
returns so that's like kind of the meta
with basian which comes back in chapter
nine as well is selecting amongst basian
models even with totally disparate
architectures is a basian model
selection question whereas in
frequentist parametric statistical
methods you can really only compare
model likelihoods using strict Al nested
the hierarchical likelihood ratio test
like
Anova but you can't test non strictly
nested
models so for all the limitations and
peculiarities of basian analysis it's
super useful to compare it to
frequentist and to non-parametric
statistical approaches like bootstrap
jack knife
resampling but those are three of the
major lineages in statistics
overall and and those are some of the
major toolkit areas as
well and the SPM textbook earlier work
by friston go goes into this and kind of
compares the methods a
lot so is the stacking kind of like
logarithmic in a sense or is there any
point where it becomes exponential and
then just falls back through the stack
to the base
what
stock well so you were saying like if
you're using basian to calculate basian
right so you're still you're kind of
using an exponential formula in a way
right but it must be within a certain
range so once you hit a maximum does it
reduce back into the root you know it's
still basian inference like you were
saying right as a four function
or would it reduce all the other layers
that you've gone through to iterate up
into a certain point right back into the
initial if there's no priors in the set
okay is an interesting question so this
is like asking what should your prior be
over structurally variant models like I
I can do the one layer temperature model
just try to do a fit I could do a two
layer temperature model three for but
then am I a
frequentist which is to say naive
over structural
parameters okay so is it like is the
whole basian game nested within a
frequentist navity about model structure
and you could do that or you could
explicitly have a prior on structure
learning so then if you were saying I'm
making structural models of this
condition in the genome and I I think
it's it's not possible for there to be
fewer than five or more than 50,000 low
side and then here's my distribution of
of structural parameters within 5 to
50,000 it's uniform within 5 to 50,000
or it's gaussian around this
number then your structure structurally
differing models would be weighted
attentionally by your prior Distribution
on that okay whereas if you have a
uniform distribution across structurally
different models that's like a fair test
across the
all okay that makes sense
thanks yeah I had a one more comment on
the chapter on page 10 the second bullet
where it starts with various cers of
active inference have possible
biological analoges in the brain it
makes they claim that Precision of
policies corresponds toil fil minerc
activity so I think again that that's a
pretty big assumption and there's a lot
going on with the regulation of
neurotransmitters and other main neurom
modulators like neur epinephrine and
serotonin so the regulation of arousal
in the brain and um the coupling the
moments of coupling between serotonin
and dopamine for for different reward
and
uh learning
circuits that are that are chained
together as well so and I think this
also relates to uh the capacity to
become aware of and pass on stimuli as
Sensations and acting on those
Sensations that impacts perception and
action and priors so I I figure I I
throw that out there
too but I I'm not sure totally
if the if other chapters in the book
press on the importance and role of
other neurotransmitters and neurom
modulators from from the top the of the
stack in terms of the of how cognition
is uh uh is
regulated within the
agent yeah here's table 51 acetylcholine
nor adrenaline and it goes it here's the
citations with some other
neurotransmitters and and um agreed it's
like it's like but there's there's so
many subtypes receptors Downstream
signaling it's like how could one single
parameter and it's like it's a course
graening it's a map it's not a teritory
it's not that it is a parameter in the
brain and then models that make unique
predictions and explanations and have
explanatory value those are leading
models and then when they when they are
fit with one data set and then they have
predicted value in a different Paradigm
again that's evidence for that it's
capturing an informational
aspect so yeah I mean thinking about
that in terms of like descending versus
ascending and deep versus superficial I
mean that's kind of the coin flip again
right where you have like at what
point in that chain of the
structure can you Det determine whether
or not the Deep has flipped to a
superficial kind of
state if we're thinking of temperature
right it's going to be a constant right
or are we talking about interval in this
case temperature could be constant or
just like from reinforcement learning
and and other basing approaches a common
method is to have a high temperature
beginning
and then turn down the temperature and
then people say well let's do
multi-chain let's have them do let's do
five parallel chains with different
temperatures and then have them swap
positions like then there's all these
higher order questions about how you
best leverage your Computing
resources but that's not changing the
analytical formalisms those are more
like computer science and engineering
methods to
Implement variational basian
methods
okay like that doesn't change the
equation of 2.5 or 2.6 but like
different approximators they may give
different results but it's like that's
like how many layers back do you pull
back in your
investigation right
question which what what's the name of
the book that you mentioned about by
friston on the SPM I think it was
earlier what's
the so the last um printed version as
far as I understand was
2007 it's purple book okay but then
there
the the SPM online documentation goes up
to 2012 and there's still a totally live
Community with people doing fmri
Imaging so I found this I found this
book to be extremely helpful background
information for several reasons first
off it's like a speed course on the
trifecta of classical parametric
statistics non-parametric statistics
basian statistics so it gets all those
in play all the time and it deals with
what we might call the a matrix the
mapping between observations and hidden
States in a setting where the
observations are of a well-known form
like EEG or fmri sensors and then the
hidden states are neural activity and
the blood oxygen flow dependent signal
the Bold fmri signal or neural activity
signals so it's like a defin system of
interest and sensor type clarifies the
setting it's not about um
multiscale um considerations but there's
some some ways towards that um so it
really hammers down the statistical and
the partially observable
part and then action selection is just
selecting a different index card in the
transition operator and changing how the
hidden State
unfolds and and that is kind of
approached towards the end of the book
in certain
analyses and it highlights the empirical
basis from your Workshop presentation
Andrew what what questions did you
receive or what did you feel like what
what what would welcome people
and um like what what did people ask and
what were they wondering when you showed
them what you
made yeah sure um yeah you know it's so
again the the conference was uh it's it
was like the big like International uh
like computational social science
conference and so many people there are
like familiar
with machine learning and and empirical
data and so on maybe not know so much um
kind of like say foundations of Concepts
in physics um information Theory and so
on um not in a way that they firmly
needed uh and so I think a lot of it's
just attempting to answer questions of
like why use active inference to try and
explain human behavior can we not
approximate human behavior through you
know iety of other methods um so it's
it's a little different from the
conversation we've been having right
like there's a lot of questions of like
scalability like oh how okay great one
person one individual entity is
minimizing their free energy but how
does that allow us to make claims about
what's going on at say more Collective
you know level like like 30 agents in a
network or something like that um you
know so it's kind of just um it's more
about
kind of describing the mentality here of
like okay we're we're creating something
like an agent based model that has an
agent and its environment and then from
there it's just you as opposed to using
like net logo which is kind of
traditional way for scientist social
scientists to do this where you have
much more rules-based logic like the
agent does X if it observes y the Z if
it observes a um you know and said it's
kind of like we have a models in a model
so we have an agent based model where
each agent is its own generative model
um so yeah it's it's just more like kind
of conceptual in that sense how to
relate it to agent based modeling human
behavior
especially
um let see what
other you know it's per usual there
there was a quick question about like
okay so why the is this a theory of
Consciousness Etc you know that they
kind of open up into other
discussions um let's see yeah I think
sorry about those massive cells there
but yeah those those outputs are like
you know this is
Agents engaging in something like
Collective problem solving so exploring
an
enk landscape where they can either uh
explore which is where they change a bit
in their own solution or they can
exploit meaning take their neighbors one
of their Network neighbors Solutions and
so the these are just like the output
results for running that over T time
steps right like how
how what what's the best solution that
they managed to collectively come up
with did all agents arrive at that
solution is it separate you could try
and use this to study something like the
the diversity of ideas in a more General
way too of like right because you know
there are fewer and fewer unique
Solutions if all agents are just jum in
to stealing the best one um so that yeah
Falls over time and then what I was
attempting to demonstrate that because
this is recreating a simulation of more
famous kind of Paradigm uh from a decade
or so ago where they try and describe
like team performance between um you
know within groups like a group of
researchers or a group of you know
employees or something all working
collectively on a problem maybe it's a
group of students right working on a
group project um but what they don't you
know it because it's all done in this
kind of like more traditional
rules-based way we're not able to look
at like okay well what about agents who
learn you know and actually adapt right
and I'm trying to demonstrate that
whenever we include these agents is
active inference agents who can learn uh
actually like the impact of engaging in
a project where you're able to just
steal your neighbor's answer without
doing much of the work yourself like if
that's kind of what you learn or adapt
to then uh then over time like that's
kind of where you'll start off your next
group project potentially like your
beliefs about what the optimal solution
is Will point you towards doing the
easier thing so so it's just kind of
trying to add a lot of more Nuance to
those that traditional simulation it
recreates the previous simulations
Dynamics it recreates the Dynamics found
in empirical literature of of group uh
Dynamics and performance and yet this by
creating agents that have these kind of
internal cognitive active inference
parameters you can you you know the idea
is to try and have proxies for like okay
what how does this impact back on the
agents themselves and the longevity of
doing practices uh practices like these
so so those like those are just some
animation plots that show like the
distribution of beliefs of uh if it's
basically mapping the likelihood of if I
see myself like exploring coming up with
my own answer you know what how does
that map to observations that are oh I'm
getting a better answer so it's kind of
like a personal
efficacy um belief it's like oh how much
do I associate exploring with a better
result a better solution in the end
which then would condition your
decisions uh over your actions like your
posteriors over policies to continue
exploring right so over time they all
start off you know kind of low that's
how I I set them up as priors but many
of them just get lower and lower like
they you know you just you have so many
neighbors that you can kind of take the
answer from so I I could go on about
this all day but it's just you know the
the the slides get into some of the more
kind of
textbook formulas equations Etc but the
the the script here was really to try
and demonstrate like what happens at a
broader scale and how could you actually
use this
um you know to approach problems that
we're already trying to get at like not
throw a bunch of new stuff at people all
at once um about here's a whole new set
of problems you can now try and approach
thanks to these methods instead it's
like here's the value added of using
these methods even whenever you try to
approach um you know existing paradigms
or problems so that's
my I ask you a question
um I haven't had a chance obviously to
look at the data but um you had
mentioned you know like uh a group of
like 30 people for example in a node if
you consider that you know one company
right let's say it's a department a
company you're still connected to
another node of say another if your n
value remains 30 per
Department um if you had you know one
individual in each of those nodes that
wasn't conforming or wasn't you know
kind of going with the same flow was
there any correlation did you see it
anywhere else in the
topology that might have affected chains
that aren't directly connected but would
be through the network
itself that's interesting
um so I didn't get quite that far right
because this was basically just kind of
put together as like a toy situ
situation right just to demonstrate but
that that's an interesting question I
think you could attempt to get it
something like that like so this is
basically just creating a single Network
like a a single
um you have two options like the way I
set up the function you can either make
a like a random graph with like P
connectivity that you can Define
yourself or you can set it up as like
subn networks um where where the the
separate subet it's like five groups of
four agents or however you you know want
to Define that but they're completely
separate from one another
but what you could do is you could
adjust that to where you know you do
have connections between the sub
networks um and then I wrote everything
you know just in a very programmatic
like make all the agents have the same
priors but you could set up an agent who
has you know very different priors from
the rest see how that plays out so I
guess the the simple answer is like I'm
not sure but the the the the tools are
kind of there if one wanted to maybe
approach and answer to that
question great thanks
sure cool maybe a model stream maybe
with somebody else who's um done it but
you should post it in Discord and let's
see if anyone plays with it and then
let's do it because I think that's a
great framework
for playing around and linking it to the
sections of the
book sounds good yeah I'm I'm I'm
someone who comes from a social science
background so it's kind of like for me
it was just kind of this plunge into
talking about like U statistical physics
and so on that it's like it's super
interesting once it it starts to catch
on but until that point it's I'm just
like thinking like how do I use this
right so that's that's exactly what I'm
trying to get at but yeah no stream
sounds really awesome so I'd be happy to
do that cool okay thank you Andrew and
cool to hear the update thank you all
for joining see you next time take care